<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Christian path-vvay Deliuered in a sermon preached at Paules Crosse, the last of Iune 1611. By Thomas Cheaste, minister and preacher of Gods Word.</title>
            <author>Cheaste, Thomas.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1613</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 72 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 24 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A18575</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 5105</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S107789</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99843484</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99843484</idno>
            <idno type="VID">8223</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A18575)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 8223)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1542:10)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Christian path-vvay Deliuered in a sermon preached at Paules Crosse, the last of Iune 1611. By Thomas Cheaste, minister and preacher of Gods Word.</title>
                  <author>Cheaste, Thomas.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[8], 40 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Nicholas Okes, dwelling neere Holborne-Bridge,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1613.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>On Ephesians V, 1.</note>
                  <note>The first leaf is blank.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Cambridge University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-08</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:8223:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8223:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THE CHRISTIAN PATH-VVAY.</p>
            <p>Deliuered in a Sermon preached <hi>at Paules Croſſe, the laſt of June</hi> 1611.</p>
            <p>By <hi>Thomas Cheaſte,</hi> Miniſter and Preacher of Gods Word.</p>
            <q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>EPHESIANS 5.1.</hi>
               </bibl>
               <p>Be yee therefore followers of God as deere Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Nicholas Okes,</hi> dwelling neere Holborne-Bridge. 1613.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:8223:2" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:8223:2"/>
            <head>TO THE RIGHT HONOVRABLE SIR IOHN SWINERTON KNIGHT, LORD MAIOR OF THE MOST HONORABLE CITTY OF <hi>London;</hi> and to the right Worſhipfull the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dermen and Shrieues of the ſame Citty; the aboundant increaſe of Spirituall Grace in this Life, and in the World <hi>to come euerlaſting Life, through Ieſus Chriſt</hi> our onely Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>S the time now approcheth wherein euery gratefull per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon will not onely in word, but alſo in deed with their preſents and giftes ſhew ſome ſigne and token of their louing and kind affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction: So (preuenting the time neere at hand) I, as a poore labourer ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uing
<pb facs="tcp:8223:3"/> gleaned &amp; gathered theſe two handsful of corne, two houres labour in the Lords Harueſt, I dedicate it (as the beſt preſent that I haue) vnto your fauourable acceptation. It may be thought great boldneſſe in mee (right Honourable and right Worſhipfull) thus preſuming to ſeeke the patronizing of this my poore endeuours vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the protection of your Honourable and Worſhipfull countenances. But if the name and nature of this my little booke bee rightly conſidered, and your dignity of place and Office therewith iuſtly weighed: this bold<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe I hope will bee thought in mee but mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſt duty, and your kinde acceptance heereof the true teſtimony of religious deuotion. I muſt confeſſe your ſerious and zealous atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in hearing this plaine Sermon when it was Preached in your preſence; and the expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rience of your religious deuotion, not onely in frequenting the ſeruice of God, but alſo in protecting and Patronizing the Preachers and Profeſſours of Gods Word, encouraged mee to preferre this my new borne Orphant, this little booke, to your graue protection, wherein I ſeeke not, as a Temporizer, to finde out matter to fit and feede Humoriſts, but in the care of a Chriſtian to make proofe of a better minde: Knowing, that your graue and reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gious mindes doe contemne idle and friuo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous flying Pamphlets: What this Booke is, your Iudgements can diſcerne, and what I am, your kindneſſe ſhall command: ſo leauing it, with my continuall prayers to Almighty God,
<pb facs="tcp:8223:3"/> that hee may direct you in the right path<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way through the vale of miſery into eternall felicity.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honours, and Worſhips in all duty. <hi>THOMAS CHEASTE.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:8223:4"/>
            <head>TO THE CHRISTIAN READER.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">G</seg>Entle Reader, the moſt skilfull Fiſher may ſometime catch a Carpe: For no doubt but there are many buſie braines, itch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing eares, taunting tongues, and carping conceipts, that will Critically play the right Momes: eſpecially thoſe that do leaſt good will finde greateſt fault with others good endeuours. But from ſuch I appeale to thy cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous and charitable cenſure (with conſideration of the want of time and health) commending this ſmall booke to thy curteous entertainment: And ſo I bid thee heartily fare-well.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:8223:4"/>
            <head>A SERMON Preached at <hi>Paules</hi> Croſſe the laſt of Inne 1611. by M. THO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MAS CHEASTE, Miniſter and <hi>Preacher of Gods</hi> WORD. THE TEXT.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>EPHESIANS 5.1.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>Be yee therefore followers of God, as deere Children.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>HE Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> right Honourable, right Reuerend, right Worſhip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full, and well-beloued in our Lord and Sauiour Chriſt, in this heauenly parcell of ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scripture, doth inſinu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate vnto vs, who are by conception ſinfull, by nature men; not perceiuing the things of God, and by life and conuerſation ſuch as doe no good: that the meanes therefore moſt fit, and the way moſt direct for the conſummating of our
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:8223:5"/> dayes, as acceptable to the Almighty, is the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>continent remouing and forſaking of all our vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ruly affections, fighting in our mindes, and the ſoule-abandoning of immoderate concupiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cence, reigning and raging in our members, by the ſuggeſtion of the Diuell; whom, with all his workes, we muſt relinquiſh, and renounce, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we can enter, bee entertained, or receiued into the holy ſeruice of Almighty God: A reaſon of this the Apoſtle ſheweth, ſaying: <hi>That there is no communion betweene light and darke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 6.14.</note> 
               <hi>no concord betwixt Chriſt and Belial, no part hath the infidell with the beleeuer.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Then let vs forſake the workes of darkneſſe, and renounce the Prince of darkneſſe, and put on the armour of light, and walke as children of the light, and follow the Prince of light. Next, let vs depoſe our ſelues from all wicked &amp; rebel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lious thoughts, words, and workes; which come by the motion, ſuggeſtion, and perſwaſion of the Diuell. And laſtly, let vs ceaſe to bee incredu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lous, and beleeue on the name of our Lord IE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SVS, and in faith apprehend him, as our onely Redeemer; that we may be ingrafted as ſonnes vnto God, and bee followers of God, as deere children: as this our Text teacheth vs.</p>
            <p>Wherein we may note an exhortation to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation; out of which (omitting all long cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances, and curious diuiſions) we may ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerue, although it is not an ordinary kinde of methode,
<list>
                  <item>1 <hi>The perſons that ſhould imitate &amp; follow.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 <hi>The imitation it ſelfe.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:8223:5" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <item>3 <hi>Thirdly, the perſon whom we ſhould follow.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 <hi>Fourthly, the manner how we ſhould follow him.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
               <list>
                  <item>1 The firſt expreſſed in theſe words: <hi>Be yee.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>2 The ſecond in this word: <hi>Followers.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>3 The third in theſe words: <hi>Of God.</hi>
                  </item>
                  <item>4 The fourth in theſe words: <hi>As deere Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren.</hi>
                  </item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Be yee therfore followers of God, as deere Children.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>[Therefore]</hi> inſinuateth a reaſon conſequent of a matter precedent, which now I omit.</p>
            <list>
               <item>Firſt to the perſons exhorted:</item>
               <item>Not onely the <hi>Epheſians,</hi> But all Chriſtians.</item>
            </list>
            <p>A Chriſtian and well-gouerned Common-wealth may bee compared to an houſe, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing builded and erected of diuers matters and ſubſtances; as ſtones for the foundation, tim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber for the erection: and other things more to bring it to perfection. So in the building of a Common-wealth there muſt be diuers orders: ſome of high degree, ſome of meane eſtate, and ſome of low condition: and all to finiſh this Houſe or Common-wealth. And as in ſumptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous buildings, one chiefe ſtone, pillar, or poſt, cannot eaſily be wrenched out, without ſhaking of all the reſt; euen as <hi>Salomons</hi> poſt vnder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>propped the whole houſe:<note place="margin">The King.</note> So the King being vnder God the ſtone, ſtay, piller, and poſt of the Common-wealth; if he miſ-carry, all the ſtrength of his Common-wealth is ſhaken, and put in hazzard of a down-fall. To auoyd therefore this
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:8223:6"/> dangerous breach in this godly building, it is the duty of all faithfull and true-hearted ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iects to pray vnto God, the King of all Kings, to giue vnto our King (his vice-roy here on earth) a wiſe &amp; an vnderſtanding heart, to giue to his Councellors the ſpirit of Councell,<note place="margin">Councell.</note> to giue to his Iudges<note place="margin">Iudges.</note> the ſpirit of Iudgement, to diſcuſſe and iudge rightly of all matters; remembring that themſelues ſhall be adiudged as well as o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers whom they haue iudged; as one ancient Father writeth.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Veniet, veniet qui iudicata reiudicabit, illicita iurata confutabit; qui faciet iuſticiam iniuriam pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tientibus, &amp; arguet in aequitate pro manſuetis terra.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>He will come, he will come, who will iudge a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine matters wrongfully iudged, who will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>proue vnlawfull oathes, will right them that ſuffer wrong, and plead in equitie for the meeke of the earth: let them thinke, that if not ſhortly, yet ſharply will the day of iudgement come to thoſe that neglect the comming of the eternall Iudge.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Veniet, veniet dies Iudicij vbi plus valebit pura corda, quam aſtuta verba; &amp; conſciencia bona, quam marſupia plena: quandoquidem Iudex ille, nec verbis falletur, nec donis flectetur.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The day will come, the day of Iudgement will come, when cleane hearts will more auaile then crafty words, and a good conſcience more then a great purſe: ſeeing that Iudge wil neither bee deceiued with words, nor weighed with gifts. But to ſpeake to them of whom moſt are
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:8223:6"/> abſent, I will abſtaine, and frame my ſpeech to them that are preſent.</p>
            <p>And ſeeing the Magiſtrate<note place="margin">Magiſtrate.</note> is one of the ſtaies, pillers, and poſts of the Common-wealth, it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>houeth him to attend his charge, aſſuring him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe that hee ſhall render an account at the laſt day, how hee hath gouerned and behaued him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe in his Magiſtracy and place; whether hee hath beene carefull to beat downe ſin, and ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſe vice: to maintain vertue, and ſupport goodneſſe; whether his eyes haue beene open in looking to his charge, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>, the people due beene op<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap> in the Lords <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                  <desc>••</desc>
               </gap>mplaints of the poore <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> laboured; whether his mouth hath beene open in giuing them comfortable an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſweres; whether his hands haue beene ready in defending them; whether his feete haue beene ſhood in haſtening to redreſſe wrongs for to ſuch ends ſhould he and all his members be ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed and imployed: to wit,
<list>
                  <item>To puniſh the nocent, and defend the innocent:</item>
                  <item>To correct the hurtful, &amp; protect the harmleſſe.</item>
                  <item>To ſuppreſſe the ſubtill, and ſupport the ſimple.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p>As the ſilly ſheepe in the ſtorme and tempeſt, running to the hedge and thicket, to ſhroud and ſhelter themſelues from the winde and weather, are oftentimes inſnared amongſt the thornes and briers, out of which, with much adoe they winde and wreſt themſelues with labour and loſſe of their wool, and in ſeeking to auoid a ſmall damage they incurre a greater danger: So
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:8223:7"/> you that are Magiſtrates, ought to looke dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gently into the dealings of your vnder Officers, leaſt that the poore man (like the ſimple and ſilly ſheepe) oftentimes being oppreſſed and wronged by his aduerſary, running to them who ſhould and ought to right them, by delaies and ſiniſter dealings is fleeced of more then he loſt before, and with the woman ſeeking for one loſt groat, leeſe the other nine; and with the man that had an hundred ſheepe, hauing loſt one, ſpend the other ninty and nine in ſuing for that on<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> for want of right looſe all.<note place="margin">Luke 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>.</note> Haue a ſpeciall regard, you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> of God, there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore, what Officers you <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap> elect, let them be well qualified;<note place="margin">Exod. 18.21.</note> 
               <hi>Iethro, Moſes</hi> father-in-law, counſelled <hi>Moſes</hi> to elect Magiſtrates and Officers being thus qualified: to wit, <hi>Men of courage; ſuch as feare God, ſuch as deale truely, and ſuch as hate couetouſneſſe:</hi> Men of courage, not fearing any mans threatning words, not proud lookes, fearing God, not fearing what man can do vnto them, dealing truely and vprightly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tweene man and man, without fauour or affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, hating couetouſneſſe, not corrupted with giftes, nor carried from the right with bribes: O happy, and twiſe happy, are the people and Common-weale whom God hath bleſſed with ſuch Magiſtrates! that Common-wealth and Country is in good eſtate where the Prince makes good Lawes, the Magiſtrates execute them, and the people obey them.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Miniſter.</note>There is alſo another ſtay of Gods building, or Chriſtian Common-wealth, which muſt not
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:8223:7" rendition="simple:additions"/> be omitted, to wit, the zealous and learned Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter, whoſe doctrine, by warrant of Gods word, muſt be a rule to guide and direct all their lawes by, otherwiſe they will be out of ſquare. Theſe Workemen ſhould not bee idle in Gods Harueſt, <hi>For the Harueſt is great, but the labourers are few.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Math. 9.37.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It is recorded in ſacred Scripture that a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine man hired labourers into his Vineyard.<note place="margin">Math. 20.</note> The owner and Maiſter of this Vineyard is the Lord, the labourers, his Miniſters and Prea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chers, the Vineyard is the world, the people the branches, but in the Lords Vineyard wee may finde ſome labourers, ſome loiterers, and ſome lookers on: <hi>Volentes, nolentes, &amp; non valentes;</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the firſt <hi>volentibus,</hi> to them that execute the Lords buſineſſe with willing mindes, reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing that God hath enabled them to doe the worke of Euangeliſts, it will be ſayd; <hi>Well done thou good ſeruant, becauſe thou haſt bene faithfull in a little, I Will make thee ruler ouer much.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the ſecond, <hi>nolentibus,</hi> to them that are able and yet not willing, it may be ſaid: <hi>Hee that knoweth his Maiſters will, and doth it not, ſhal be beaten with ſtripes.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>To the third and laſt, <hi>non valentibus</hi> (without offence I may ſay the worſt) that are neither able nor willling, it may bee ſaid: <hi>Thou vnbidden gueſt, how camſt thou in? at the dore, or at the window?</hi> ſurely not at the dore, vnleſſe thou haſt borrowed <hi>Simon Magus</hi> ſiluer piclocke,<note place="margin">Math. 22.12.]</note> 
               <hi>Friend how camſt thou hither, not hauing a wedding gar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? take him, bind him hand and foote, and caſt
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:8223:8"/> him into vtter darkneſſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Let vs pray vnto God that euery <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> well-ruling Elder, ſuffer no vnruled &amp; vnlearned loo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kers &amp; gazers on, to ſteale into the Lords Vine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yard, who are ready to receiue the penny and take no paines; to take the fleece, and ſtarue the ſheepe: too too many ſuch in times paſt haue crept in,<note place="margin">Math. 13.28.</note> but how came this to paſſe? <hi>ſurely, the enuious man hath done this:</hi> Therefore right Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend, you, to whom by authority it appertai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth, ought now to bee carefull and reſpectiue herein, leſt that the aduerſaries of our profeſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, by the ignorance and weakeneſſe of ſome Profeſſors: take an occaſion by ſuch aduantage to ſcandalize, both the profeſſion and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſours, to defend this dangerous breach in Gods building, you ought to bee ſtudious and vigilant:<note place="margin">Math. 13.25.</note> 
               <hi>For when the husbandman ſleepeth, the enuious man will be ready to ſow the tares amongſt the wheate;</hi> And ſo by your zealous care ouer the Lords heritage, his Vineyard in time might bee cleanſed from ſuch lookers and gazers on: and his Church purged of ſuch penny-father idols: and hereafter ſuch ignorant tongue-tied blind guides debarred by ſuch your good meanes from entring into the Lords Vineyard. Which God for his Name ſake, for his Sonnes ſake, for his mercy ſake, for his Church and deere children ſake grant: Thus much touching the perſons eſpeciall, now in generall.</p>
            <div type="part">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:8223:8"/>
               <head>
                  <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap>.<note place="margin">Ephe. 5.1.</note>
               </head>
               <p>EVEN as Chriſt fed foure thouſand men,<note place="margin">Math. 15.33.34.35.</note> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides women and children, with ſeuen loaues and a few little fiſhes, when they had followed him three daies, in the deſert or wilderneſſe, and would not ſend them away empty, leaſt they ſhould faint by the way.</p>
               <p>So with theſe ſeuen loaues of the bread of life, are fed foure thouſand, yea forty thouſand, yea thouſand thouſands of men, women, and children (for women and children haue ſoules to ſaue as well as men:) if we, according to our Text, follow him in the deſert of this wide world, (no wider then wicked) three daies in the true faith of the Trinity, God will not ſend vs away emptie, nor ſuffer our ſoules for want of ſpirituall food to faint. <hi>Therefore, let vs bee fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowers of him as deere children:</hi> and be ready to obey this precept of imitation, which is the ſecond part of this our Text to be intreated of.</p>
               <p>If we enter into due conſideration of mans nature,<note place="margin">Imitation it ſelfe.</note> wee ſhall finde it ſtrangely addicted to imitation; and although in truth we ſhould liue by lawes more then by examples, yet wee ſhall perceiue, that examples do more moue in theſe daies then lawes; ſeruants in a family, ſouldiours in an army, ſubiects in a Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon-weale may co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme this to be true, for Seruants moſt co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>monly imitate their Maiſters, Soldiers their Captains, Subiects their Gouernours, bee they good, bee they bad, get they praiſe, or diſpraiſe, profite or diſprofite, fame or infamy thereby: thinking
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:8223:9"/> their liues to be a Law, and that to be well done, which is done after their example.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Note </seg>1</label> Whereby we may note firſt, that they ſhould haue regard vnto themſelues, who are any way either for birth or for office, or for calling, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther it bee ſpirituall or temporall, aboue other men; for they cannot ſinne without great dan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to the Common-weale, we may ſay of ſuch, as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaid of Iudges, <hi>that mighty men, ſhould mightely be tormented.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Note </seg>2</label> Secondly, ſeeing our nature is prone to imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tation, wee are to take ſpeciall care whom wee follow or imitate: for euery one is not to bee followed, neither ſhall the vngodly behauiour of others excuſe vs before God, the reaſon is: <hi>Wee muſt all appeare before the tribunall ſeate of Chriſt,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 5.10. Reuel. 22.12.</note> 
                  <hi>to receiue according to our owne deeds.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The licentious life of the Magiſtrate, ſhall not excuſe the Subiect if hee liue not vnder the Law, nor the wicked life of the Maiſter, acquit the Seruant, if hee be vngracious, nor the euill conuerſation of the Preacher be a cauſe to ſaue the hearer if he be vngodly: the reaſon is, <hi>for that ſoule that ſinneth</hi> (whatſoeuer hee bee) <hi>ſhall die.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Ezech. 18.4.</note>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Two kinds of examples. 1 Of Chriſt. 2 Of man.</note>In Chriſtian imitation there are two kinds of examples to be folowed: The one both neceſſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry and alwaies, the other but ſometime and in ſome things, neceſſary and alwaies, the example of our Lord and Sauiour Chriſt, but ſometime and in ſome things, the examples of good men and women are to be followed.</p>
               <p>Strange it may ſeeme to ſome, that good men
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:8223:9"/> but ſometime, and in ſome things, are to bee followed; yet it is not ſo ſtrange as true, for euery example of theirs is not to bee followed of vs, for the better conceiuing whereof wee may note that there are foure examples<note place="margin">4 <hi>Examples.</hi>
                  </note> of the faithfull, and elect, in ſacred Scriptures.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Example. </seg>1</label> The firſt we may behold and follow: as <hi>Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hams</hi> faith, <hi>Ioſephs</hi> chaſtity, <hi>Dauids</hi> zeale, <hi>Tobias</hi> pittifulneſſe towards the poore, and ſuch like: theſe are looking-glaſſes ſet before our eies, that wee ſhould not bee ſlothfull in following them, but follow them as they follow Chriſt, which through faith and patience inherite the promiſes.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Example. </seg>2</label> Other examples there are which are wicked, as <hi>Dauids</hi> adultery, <hi>Peters</hi> deniall, the Apoſtles ambition, and ſuch like: which are not recorded in deſpite to diſgrace them, but are placed be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore vs, for theſe three ends:<note place="margin">3 <hi>Ends:</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Firſt, to keepe vs from vaine opinion of our ſelues, that wee pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſume not in our owne ſtrength: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> Secondly, to make vs the more carefull to looke to our ſteps that we ſlip not as they did, for feare that wee cannot riſe as they did; it is eaſy to fall, but hard to ariſe: <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Thirdly, if we haue fallen, as they did, we ſhould by their example learne to riſe, as they did; if we haue like ſinnes wee ſhould haue like repentance.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Example. </seg>3</label> Other examples were well done by good men, in times paſt, which in theſe daies we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not, nor may follow, without great offence to God: as circumciſion of the male children, of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten and ſundry bloudy ſacrifices, which now to
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:8223:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> do is ſinne.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Example. </seg>4</label> Fourthly, and finaly, ſome examples, as wee may reade, were ſingular, ſuch, as neither wee, nor others in thoſe daies might follow, without the eſpeciall, and extraordinary motion of the holy Spirit, as <hi>Abrahams</hi> readineſſe to offer vp his ſonne in ſacrifice; The ſpoiling of <hi>Aegypti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> in robbing them of their Iewels and trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſures, commendable in them, becauſe they were commanded; but damnable in vs becauſe wee are forbidden, to them the one acceptable, the other commendable; but in vs, the one the next degree to murther, the other to theft, whereby we may note that good men in all things are not to bee followed:<note place="margin">2. Cor. 11.1.</note> but as Saint <hi>Paul</hi> would bee followed, as hee followed Chriſt, ſo ſhould they bee.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>Now to the perſon whom we ſhould follow, to wit, <hi>CHRIST.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>VVHen I was called heretofore to this place, by the warrant of Gods word, I deliuered certaine documents wherin we might learne, <hi>The way to Life;</hi> and now in this Text we may learne whom wee ſhould follow, as our guide in <hi>the way to Life:</hi> namely, CHRIST.</p>
               <p>Graue and iudicious Audients, Chriſt is the example, of vs to be followed; and that alwaies and neceſſary: Alwayes, for that he is moſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly good: And neceſſary, becauſe both hee and his Apoſtles haue commanded vs ſo to do.</p>
               <p>Yet I pray you miſtake me not: for all-be-it I
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:8223:10" rendition="simple:additions"/> ſay, our Sauiour Chriſt is alwayes; yet do I not ſay, in all things: and although neceſſary to bee followed, yet not as hee is God: for hee faſted 40. dayes, and 40. nights, hee raiſed the dead, gaue ſight to the blinde, and many other mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles by the Almighty power of his God-head: hee wrought things vn-able to bee imitated of mortall men.</p>
               <p>In theſe things which our Sauiour Chriſt did, as he is God, he is moſt religiouſly to bee wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhipped: and in theſe things which hee did, as man, he is zealouſly to be followed. He that lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth and hateth what Chriſt, as God, doth loue and loath, doth follow Chriſt as farre as a man may follow God. Hee that doth that which Chriſt did, as man, doth follow Chriſt as a Chriſtian man ſhould do.</p>
               <p>We ought to abhorre the vanity of this world,<note place="margin">Bernard.</note> and that cuoragiouſly, becauſe IESVS would not bee elected a King, hee fled from the multi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tude: to repent, and that heartily; for IESVS was killed as a Lambe: to haue true Charity; for IESVS prayed for his enemies. Chriſtians haue their names of Chriſt; therefore it is meet, as they are co-heires of his name, ſo ſhould they be followers of his holineſſe. No man is rightly called a Chriſtian, who to the vttermoſt of his power, doth not reſemble Chriſt, in life and conuerſation: he that followeth not Chriſt, may bee called a Chriſtian; but is none. So Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Auguſtine.</note> ſaith: What doth it profite thee, to be called a Chriſtian, whereas thou art not? to vſurpe a ſtrange name? If thou loueſt to
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:8223:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> bee called a Chriſtian, ſhew the fruits of Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity; and then well mayeſt thou take the name of a Chriſtian vnto thee.</p>
               <p>Whereas by naturall inclination wee are ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicted to imitation, let vs follow the beſt: wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome would ſo; partly becauſe we are <hi>Engliſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men,</hi> who are reported, aboue all other nations, to be famous or infamous in imitating and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing euery ſtrange and new-found faſhion. Many haue gotten fame in imitating <hi>Cicero</hi> in eloquence, <hi>Ariſtotle</hi> in Philoſophy, <hi>Iuſtinians</hi> in Law; and <hi>Galen</hi> in Phyſicke, and ſuch like. But more haue gotten ſhame in imitating one Country in vanity, another in luxurie: the Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh, in brauery; the Italian, in letchery; the Barbarian, in cruelty; the Turke, in incredulity; the Grecian, in Gluttony; the Papiſt, in Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try; the Atheiſt, in impiety; and the Libertine, in impurity: and not in following our Sauiour Chriſt in heauenly wiſedome and godlineſſe of maners.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Paul</hi> admoniſhing the Coloſſians to an imitation of Chriſt and his holineſſe,<note place="margin">Coloſſ. 3.5.</note> firſt ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horteth them to mortification; as though with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out that meanes it were impoſſible: <hi>Mortifie therefore your members vpon earth,</hi> and giueth a reaſon of his exhortation, ſaying; <hi>If yee liue af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fleſh yee ſhall dye.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Rom. 8.13.</note> As God commanded <hi>Moſes</hi> to put off his ſhooes before hee ſhould approach neere him, ſo God commandeth vs to put away all our ſinfull affections before wee begin to follow Chriſt: he will haue vs to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake our ſinnes before he will ſuffer vs to follow
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:8223:11" rendition="simple:additions"/> him. As <hi>Peter</hi> forſooke his boats, nets and all, and followed Chriſt: ſo ſhould wee leaue all worldly gaine and commodity, and follow Chriſt. <hi>Matthew</hi> left his office of cuſtome (al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though it was gainfull vnto him) and followed Chriſt: So ſhould we reſigne all worldly gaine and riches, and follow Chriſt, who will make vs rich in him. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label> It may bee ſome will demaund why <hi>Peter</hi> often vſed his former trade of life, and <hi>Matthew</hi> neuer returned to his office? <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                  </label> It may eaſily be anſwered: <hi>Peter</hi> was a fiſher-man, and did get his liuing by his lawfull paines, and honeſt meanes and labour; but <hi>Mathewes</hi> Cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome-office was very ſeldome, or neuer execu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted without corruption: and therefore it was vnlawfull for him, being a follower of Chriſt, to returne to it againe.<note place="margin">1. Kings. 19.20.</note> 
                  <hi>Eliſha</hi> left his Plow and Oxen, and followed <hi>Elias:</hi> ſo ſhould wee leaue oxen, lands, houſe, country, kindred; yea our ſelues, rather then forſake Chriſt.</p>
               <p>In following Chriſt we muſt trauell the right way: wee may finde in ſacred Scriptures, two wayes proponed, the one ſtraight and narrow,<note place="margin">Math. 7.13.14. Luke 13.24.</note> the other wide and broade: the one leadeth to life, the other to death: the one to heauen, the other to hell: The one ſtraight and narrow in the beginning, but broad and pleaſant in the end: the other wide and broad in the begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, but ſtraight and painfull in the end. The one in the beginning, <hi>Take vp thy croſſe and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low me:</hi> but in the end, <hi>Feare not my little flocke, for it is your fathers will to giue you a kingdome.</hi> The other in the beginning, <hi>All the world, and
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:8223:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> the riches therof, will I giue thee, if thou wilt wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip me</hi> (ſaith Sathan:) but in the end, <hi>Take him, binde him hand and foot, and caſt him into vtter darkneſſe.</hi> In the one a good change, from a croſſe to a kingdome: In the other a bad change; from a kingdome to a priſon, and dungeon of vtter darkeneſſe. Leaue therefore the broad and wide way, for it leadeth to deſtruction, and walke in the narrow and ſtraight way, for it leadeth to life.</p>
               <p>If thou wilt follow Chriſt, thou muſt trauell his way; not a broad, pleaſant, wide, and delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full way, full of pleaſure, wantonneſſe, &amp; world<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ioyes: but a narrow, troubleſome, &amp; ſtraight way, full of afflictions, croſſes, tribulations and ſorrowes. All men, as long as they liue in this vale of miſery, ſhall haue their part of miſery; euery man ſhall haue his turne of ſorrow, more or leſſe, one time or other; which way ſoeuer we walke, we ſhall heare euery man complaine of ſome ſorrow or miſery. What ſhall wee doe then? Before it come, let vs prepare our ſelues for it: when it is come, bid it welcome, and beare it patiently: when it is departing, giue it but halfe a fare-well, ſtill expecting when it will re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turne againe. Yet keepe thou this narrow way, and follow Chriſt, and thou ſhalt bee ſafe, and finde reſt vnto thy ſoule: but if thou wander out of this way, into the pleaſant paths of ſinne, and turne thy backe to God, and leaue his pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tection, there is no helpe for thee, Sathan will take thee priſoner, leade thee captiue, binde thee hand and foot, and caſt thee into the deepe
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:8223:12" rendition="simple:additions"/> dungeon of darkneſſe. For this aſſure thy ſelfe; If thou wilt not follow Chriſt, Sathan will fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low thee: Be not like theſe idle Epicures, and careleſſe ſlacke-graces, who liue as though they had no ſoules to ſaue, as though there were nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther God nor Diuell, no ioyes in heauen, nor torments in hell; leſt thou looſe the one, to thy griefe, &amp; finde the other, to thy endleſſe paine. If thou wilt not follow Chriſt in the way towards heauen, do not think that thou ſhalt eſcape hell; there is no ſtarting-hole betweene both for thee couertly to hide thy ſelfe: the Angell that fell from God, with all his adherents, could finde no ſuch place; none of <hi>Adams</hi> children could ſo ſhrowd themſelues, but they were found out. <hi>Diues</hi> could finde no place betweene heauen and hell to ſtay him from torments, but needes he muſt into them.</p>
               <p>Conſider therefore thine eſtate; to heauen thou canſt not come, but by following of <hi>Chriſt. No man commeth to the Father</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>but by me.</hi> Hee is gone to prepare a place for none but for them that follow him.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label> It may be, thou thinkeſt thy ſoule, being diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lodged, and diſburdened of the heauy weight of the body, ſhall flye, as a bird, into heauen. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                  </label> O bee not deceiued, if thou dye in a reprobate e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtate, thou ſhalt finde and feele that thy ſoule hath loſt her wings: that is, the ſanctified <hi>Will, Memory,</hi> and <hi>Vnderſtanding,</hi> the three golden wings of the faithfull ſoule.</p>
               <p>
                  <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Obiection. </seg>
                  </label> Againe, it may be thou thinkeſt, that when thy ſoule ſhall depart from the body, it ſhall bee
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:8223:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> freed from all earthly things whatſoeuer; and that no terreſtriall matter ſhall cleaue vnto it, neither can it ſinne when it is freed from the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full fleſh. <label type="milestone">
                     <seg type="milestoneunit">Anſwere. </seg>
                  </label> True it is, that when the ſoule is de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>parted from the body, it cannot then commit a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny more ſinne, becauſe it wanteth the body, whoſe members are as the tooles &amp; inſtruments to execute the wickedneſſe of the ſinfull ſoule: but all-be-it the ſoule is departed from the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy, yet ſinne is not departed from the ſoule: for theſe two, to wit, <hi>Sinne,</hi> and an accuſing <hi>Conſcience,</hi> will cleaue cloſly to an impenitent ſoule: theſe it ſhall bee ſure of; no other thing ſhall it haue with it from the earth, but ſinne, wherein it delighted, and a guilty conſcience, ſaying (as it were) we are thy ſinnes, we will not leaue thee, but follow and accompany thee vnto death, in death, after death, vnto iudgement, in iudgement, after iudgement, and for euer. O careleſſe man! remember in time, that the im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>penitent ſinner, of all his worldly ioyes, wealth, pleaſures and delights, ſhall haue nothing to comfort him; but his ſinnes and a guilty con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience cleauing faſt vnto him, vn-remoueable, that neuer-dying worme, alwaies biting and gnawing on his ſorrowfull ſoule.</p>
               <p>Therefore in time mortifie thy ſinnes (before it bee too late) that they may not mortifie thy ſoule: for the hazard of eternall life dependeth on the dying or not dying of ſinne; and that ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily. Who is ſo voyd of vnderſtanding, as not to thinke it expedient and neceſſary wiſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome rather to deſtroy ſinne, then himſelfe: for
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:8223:13" rendition="simple:additions"/> one of the two muſt needs bee mortified, either ſinne, or the ſoule, muſt ſuffer death and dye. Therefore ſpare not ſinne, but mortifie it, cruſh the ſerpents head betimes, kill all thy ſinnes, bee partiall to none: for one darling ſinne is enough to binde thee faſt vnto Sathan, ſeeing it is eaſie to hold him that ſtriueth not to depart: One kinde of ſin may kill thy ſoule as well as an hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred, and bring death which is eternall vpon thee. Remember <hi>Saul,</hi> and forget not thy ſoule,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 15.</note> God commanded him vtterly to deſtroy the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>malekites;</hi> he ſparing but ſome of them, was caſt off from God, and his kingdome rent from him. Our ſinnes are the <hi>Amalekites,</hi> which God com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth vs to deſtroy: wee muſt kill them all, and ſpare none; wee muſt not ſpare <hi>Agag,</hi> wee muſt not ſpare any captaine ſinne, leſt God for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake vs, and ſo we looſe a better kingdome then euer <hi>Saul</hi> found.</p>
               <p>As <hi>Amelek</hi> reſiſted the children of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in their iourney towards the land of promiſe:<note place="margin">Deut. 25.17.</note> ſo Sathan ſeeketh by all meanes, to hinder and let vs in following Chriſt, and forſaking ſin. Theſe two obſtacles hee trumpeth in our way to ſtop vs from our conuerſion: to wit,
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>Delectatio peccandi,</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>&amp; audacia defendendi.</hi> That is,</item>
                     <item>Delight of ſinning, and</item>
                     <item>Boldneſſe of defending.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Peccatum quatuor modis perpetratur in corde, quatuor<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> modis conſummatur in opere.</hi> Sin is foure
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:8223:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> manner of wayes committed in heart, and foure manner of wayes finiſhed in action: That is, in heart
<list>
                     <item>
                        <hi>By ſuggeſtion. Suggeſtion</hi> cometh by the Diuell.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>By delight. Delight</hi> by the fleſh.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>By conſent. Conſent</hi> by the ſpirit.</item>
                     <item>
                        <hi>By boldneſſe of defending ſin. Boldneſſe of defence</hi> by our elati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on ſtubbornneſſe.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>With theſe foure ſtrokes the old and enuious aduerſary of mankinde, vndermined and ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>threw the vprightneſſe of the firſt man: the Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent perſwaded, <hi>Eue</hi> delighted, <hi>Adam</hi> conſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted; and when hee was vrged to confeſſe his fault, he defended it by audacious excuſe. After ſuggeſtion commeth delight, after delight com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth defending of ſinne.</p>
               <p>As (ſaith <hi>Chryſoſtome</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Chryſoſtome.</note>) it is impoſſible to kindle fire with water, ſo it is impoſſible to ſtirre vp re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance or conuerſion in a man that delight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth in ſinne: for as water doth quench the fire, and not kindle it, ſo delight in ſinne doth bury repentance, and not reuiue it. Therefore the Prophet <hi>Dauid</hi> deſireth God to keepe him from ſinne, and from delight in ſinne; fearing leſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſumptuous ſinnes ſhould haue the vpper hand of him. And the Apoſtle Saint <hi>Paul</hi> exhor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth vs to mortifie our earthly members, as the beſt way to cut off the delight of ſinne, that ſin may dye.</p>
               <p>I reade in a pretty familiar hiſtory, (not im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertinent to this purpoſe) that there was a cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine boy, hauing a great delight to play with a
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:8223:14" rendition="simple:additions"/> bird, tied a thrid to the legge of the bird, and ſate downe and plaied therewith, letting the bird come and goe at his pleaſure, <hi>Anſelmus</hi> a godly man comming vnto him, grieuing to ſee him liue that idle and euill kind of life, cut the thrid: ſo the bird did flie away, and the boy aroſe and led a better kind of life. Morally, it may bee well applied thus, this boy may ſignifie a ſinner, this bird, ſinne, this thrid, delight in ſinne, his ſitting downe his continuance in ſinne, taking pleaſure therein, and making paſtime to ſinne at his pleaſure: This <hi>Anſelmus</hi> may ſignifie true re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pentance and vnfeigned conuerſion in a man, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tending and fully purpoſing to forſake ſinne and follow Chriſt, which cutteth the thrid, that is the delight of ſinne, ſinne dieth, and the ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner (well termed a boy for his childiſh and foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh actions) riſeth vp, that is, ſitteth and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinueth not in ſinne, but leadeth henceforth a more ſanctified kinde of life.</p>
               <p>Saint <hi>Iohn</hi> in his Epiſtle generall,<note place="margin">1. Ioh. 2.15.</note> exhorting men to follow Chriſt, dehorteth them from the loue of the world and the delight of ſinne reigning in them that loue the world: ſaying, <hi>Loue not the world, nor the things in the world:</hi> a reaſon in the 16 verſe<note place="margin">Verſe 16.</note> he giueth ſaying; <hi>For all that is in the world</hi> (as the luſt of the fleſh, the luſt of the eie, and the pride of life) <hi>is not of the Father, but of the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The world, is as the deuils golden cheine, to hinder men from following of Chriſt, which treaſure he offereth to beſtow on them that will forſake God, and follow him; and therefore hee
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:8223:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> would haue giuen it, and all the riches thereof, to our Lord and Sauiour Chriſt, but it was none of his to giue, hee was but an vſurper: Therefore as our Lord and Maiſter Chriſt deni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed him, ſo let vs, his ſeruants, defie him, and as the ſame Apoſtle maketh (as it were) anatomy of certaine great ſins in which men ſo delight; ſo let vs by his admonition hate &amp; deteſt them, and ſhun the way to hell, as hell it ſelfe; amongſt other capitall ſinnes which hinder and let vs from following Chriſt, heere are three by the Apoſtle pointed out, to wit; <hi>couetouſneſſe, pride, and voluptuouſneſſe:</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Colloſſ. 3.5.</note> coueteouſneſſe, although it be accounted good husbandry, and frugality: yet the Apoſtle <hi>Paul</hi> calleth it a let,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 5.5.</note> and idolatry: idolatry becauſe men ſo much loue and em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brace it; a let, becauſe it keepeth vs backe from following Chriſt; if it bee idolatry, how can couetous men be good Chriſtians, ſeeing they loue the world more then Chriſt? if it bee a bar to keepe men from heauen, how doe couetous men thinke it poſſible to enter through the eye of an needle, being ſwollen with this ſinne as great as a Camell? if men were ſo couetous of the Kingdome of heauen, as they are greedy of worldly wealth, they would not take ſo much paines in getting of it, and ſo little labour in fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing of Chriſt: but we may finde it true, That <hi>Impij alacriùs currunt ad mortem quam pij ad vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tam:</hi> The vngodly runne more haſty to death, then the godly to life; they take more paines for deſtruction, then others for ſaluation.</p>
               <p>For coueteouſneſſe hath no pleaſure in it,
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:8223:15" rendition="simple:additions"/> but great trouble and miſery; for it is a trouble to the body, diſquietneſſe to the minde, and a griefe to the heart, it pincheth and pricketh with three great and deepe wounds: The firſt to the bone, the ſecond to the braine, the third to the heart; to the bones in tiring and wearying men in getting riches: to the braines, in great care to keepe them being gotten, as pricking thornes amongſt the which the diuine ſeede of Gods words ſowen fructifieth not.<note place="margin">Math. 13.8.9.</note> The laſt cut which is moſt greiuous that is to the heart, in leauing and loſing them, yea, and with his owne ſelfe, his owne ſoule, his owne life, yea life both of body and ſoule, too deere a price for ſo vile a thing, in ſelling his ſoule for ſinne, Therefore Chriſt ſaith:<note place="margin">Math. 16.26.</note> 
                  <hi>What ſhall it auaile me to winne the whole world, and looſe mine owne ſoule?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Let vs remember the couetous caterpillar, and meale-mouthed Farmer, that was not con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tented with his barnes full of Corne and much wealth, how hee was in a monent ſatisfied with a mouthfull of duſt, and, which was moſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mentable, his ſoule taken from him; I feare hee hath many ſons this day liuing, whom I would haue take notice hereof, and ſee Gods iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment is ſuch, that their wealth ſhall bee turned into woe, their plenty into ſcarcity, their proſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perity into pouerty, their ſolace into ſorrow, their gladneſſe into ſadneſſe, their mirth into mourning, their pleaſure into paine, their tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quility into calamity.</p>
               <p>I reade in ancient writing,<note place="margin">Iſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>od.</note> that old men did picture <hi>Mercury,</hi> one of the Planets, like to a
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:8223:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> couetous Merchant, hauing in his mouth a thorny tongue, with wings ſpread abroad in the middeſt, ſeeming glittering gold, and vpon his head a cocke: The morallity of this ſtory may be thus applied: The thorny tongue may repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent the deceiptfull words, falſe oaths, and fraudulent dealing of cruell couetous men, in bargaining, buying, and ſelling with men: The wings may repreſent the haſt, ſpeed, and celeri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty that coueteous men vſe in gathering of wealth, in trauelling from Market to Market, from Towne to Towne, from Kingdome to Kingdome, ouer Sea and Land, omitting no time, occaſion, or oportunity: Glittering and ſhining may ſignifie the gaine of gold, ſeeming like fire, for gold may bee compared to fire, a little whereof is ſufficient to warme a man, but too much burneth: Gold &amp; gaine, in good, ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt, and lawfull ſort gotten, proſpereth with a man, but by vniuſt and vnlawfull manner ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thered damneth a man: Well gotten, and well vſed it helpeth, but wickedly gotten and wicked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly vſed it hurteth.</p>
               <p>The cocke repreſenteth the carefull vigilan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy that poſſeſſeth couetous mens minds, who riſe vp earely and lie downe late, taking their reſt but vntill the cocke croweth, or the clocke ſtriketh.</p>
               <p>Thus the deſcription of a couetous mans life is expreſſed: and <hi>Iob</hi> hath a notable Epitaph at his death, to be ingraued vpon his Tomb, <hi>Hee is dried vp and withered,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iob. 6.17.</note> 
                  <hi>and in time conſumed, and when it is hot he falleth from his place; before he
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:8223:16" rendition="simple:additions"/> departeth from his way and courſe of life:</hi> A wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thy note for ſhunning the like, and a fearefull iudgement vpon them that follow the coue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tous affections of this wicked world, and for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſake Chriſt whom they are bound to follow vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on forfeiture of ſaluation, and paine of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demnation.</p>
               <p>Let vs not ſettle our affections vpon earthly things, hunting after the vnſatiable deſire of worldly wealth, like the mole or want that ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keth many holes and diggeth many dennes in the earth, and yet is not ſatisfied but ſtill labou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth and diggeth: Let vs not build many houſes, digge many ſellars, buy many Farmes, fill many barnes, and yet bee vnſatiable and vnthankfull, and in all our aboundance and plenty will not ſay, <hi>Bleſſed be the name of the Lord,</hi> which <hi>Iob</hi> did in his greateſt pouerty: The couetous cormo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant when his barnes were full and his houſe fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed, was ſatisfied, ſaying as it were, <hi>Soule thou haſt ſufficient, eate, drinke, take thine eaſe;</hi> But ſome hauing enough, and more then enough, are not ſatisfied, but would with ſathan com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe the whole world if they might: Seeing therefore that couetouſneſſe keepeth vs from following Chriſt, the ready way to heauen, and leadeth vs the headlong way to hell, let vs as the Apoſtle exhorteth: <hi>Bee followers of God, as deere children.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The other let that holdeth men backe from following God, is Pride, and it is no ſmall ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>my to mankind, although now it is accompted no ſinne: It cauſed the Angell with many his
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:8223:17" rendition="simple:additions"/> Aſſociates to looſe heauen, it cauſed <hi>Adam</hi> and <hi>Eue</hi> to looſe Paradice, and it will bee a cauſe to exclude and debarre vs of the Kingdome of heauen, vnleſſe wee humble our ſelues and fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low Chriſt, as dutifull ſchollars, learning the leſſon which he hath taught vs, ſaying: <hi>Learne of mee, for I am humble and meeke of heart:</hi> Againe hee ſaith, <hi>Hee that exalteth himſelfe ſhall bee brought low;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prouerb. 16.18</note> Salomon telleth, <hi>that pride goeth before, and deſtruction followeth after:</hi> And the old Writer <hi>Gregory</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gregory.</note> ſaith: <hi>As humilty is a ſigne of election and approbation, ſo pride is a ſigne of reie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction and reprobation.</hi> Pride may fitly be compa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red to a pale horſe,<note place="margin">Reuel. 6.8.9.</note> 
                  <hi>The name of him that rideth thereon is death, and hell followeth after:</hi> Pale it is, for that it wanteth the cheerefull and comfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>table complexion of godly charity, and death rideth on it, for death is the wages of pride, which the deuill knew right well, who by pride brought ſpirituall death on all, and hell follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth after, being the place prepared for all proud perſons, who are betraied by pride in their owne bodies and members: As <hi>Abſolon</hi> conſpired his fathers death by offering giftes to his fathers ſubiects: And <hi>Eue</hi> for a proud minde to bee like vnto God, was made more vnlike, and defaced the image of God in her ſelfe, and thereby loſt Paradice: Pride is a ſinne that God hateth; all other ſins flie from God, but pride ſtubbornely ſtandeth with the hauty Phariſee and faceth with God: Therefore, he that will bee a follower of Chriſt muſt forſake pride.</p>
               <pb n="27" facs="tcp:8223:17" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>For a proud man is
<list>
                     <item>1 <hi>Deo odibilis</hi> To God odible</item>
                     <item>2 <hi>Diabolo ſimilis</hi> Like to the diuil</item>
                     <item>3 <hi>&amp; ſibi damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bilis.</hi> and to himſelfe damnable.</item>
                  </list>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Three ſortes of men my ſoule hateth, &amp;c.</hi> 
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> The firſt whereof is a proud man:<note place="margin">Eccle. 25.2.</note> examples in the Angels, and in men wee haue in no ſmall num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="2"/> The deuill is the Prince of pride, and father of proud men, and as the ſeruants of Chriſt, and children of God are knowne by charity and humility; ſo the ſeruants of ſinne and ſonnes of Sathan, are knowne by pride and cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eltie.</p>
               <p>
                  <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="3"/> Hee is hurtfull to himſelfe, Examples wee haue, amongſt diuers others, of <hi>Ieſabell,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Reu. 18 7. Eſay 47.8.</note> of the proud ſtrumpet of <hi>Babylon,</hi> of <hi>Senecharib,</hi> &amp;c. who ſoaring aloft with their proud plumes, being at the higheſt pitch of their exaltation, were throwne downe head-long and plunged in the deepe lake and dungeon of deſtruction, and as the wolfe followeth the prey, and the Hunter followeth the wolfe to deſtroy him: ſo as man followeth pride, puniſhment followeth proud men to deſtroy them. <hi>Vir<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſcelus ſequitur paena<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> iuſta virum.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Now the third let that hindereth vs in fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowing Chriſt is voluptuouſneſſe, which al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though in our time it is accompted but a ſport: yet it is a canker that eateth vp vertue in a man which is eternall:<note place="margin">Auguſtine.</note> This vice old men ſhould
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:8223:18"/> loath, and yong men ſhould leaue, but by experi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence many, yea too many yong men, being trai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vp by their carefull parents, either in vertu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous ſchools, or honeſt trades of life, leaue man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners with their Maiſters, vertue in the ſchools, &amp; run aſtray with the prodigal ſon, luxuriouſty ſpe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding their portions: others, leauing their trades with their Maiſters, &amp; ſcience in the ſhops; with <hi>Eſau</hi> ſell their Birth-right for a meſſe of volup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuous pottage, in the kitchin of wantonneſſe ſpending their time in ſathans Synagogue of wickedneſſe: The more pitty that they haue ſo little piety, ſeeing it is not the loſſe onely of Temporall goods, but the loſſe of the Kingdom of heauen; and one ancient father ſaith; <hi>Iuſtum eſt vt qui peccata vti voluiſſet aeternaliter ſi potuiſſet, aeternaliter paenam ſuſtinere cogeretur,</hi> it is requi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſite that hee that would vſe ſinne alwaies, if hee could, ſhould continually bee conſtrained to ſuffer puniſhment, which that wee may eſcape let vs both old and yong ceaſe to be voluptuous and turne to be zealous in following of Chriſt, for as long as wee harbour this vice in our hearts, wee carry (as <hi>Vrias</hi> did) letters to our owne deſtruction, and as long as wee greedily follow after it, we do follow it (as <hi>Aſahel</hi> follow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>Abner</hi>) to our owne death.</p>
               <p>Thus wee may ſee theſe great, groſſe, and grieuous ſinnes do ſtoppe, dampe, and rampire the way againſt vs to keepe vs out of heauen, as they excluded our firſt parents out of Paradiſe, and thereby diſplaced &amp; diſ-inherited vs of the poſſeſſion and intereſt thereof, if wee hate him
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:8223:18" rendition="simple:additions"/> that vndermineth &amp; beguileth vs of our earthly inheritance, as <hi>Eſau</hi> hated his brother <hi>Iacob:</hi> how much more ſhould we deteſt theſe ſins, that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraud vs of our celeſtiall habitation?</p>
               <p>We do exceedingly hate him that killeth our father or mother: how much more then ſhould we hate theſe ſins that haue brought death and mortality vpon all our parents, our ſelues and our poſterity.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The ſecond Obſtacle. <hi>Audacia defenſionis.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>THe ſecond obſtacle that fettereth the feet of our affection, is the boldneſſe of defen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding or excuſing ſin: this was in <hi>Adam</hi> after hee had tranſgreſſed by co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mitting the foreſaid ſins, beeing vrged by Almighty God to confeſſe his fault, ſtill defended &amp; excuſed his offences: So there are many of <hi>Adams</hi> children that will not (although they ſee and know their owne naked<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe) co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſe it: but are leſſe aſhamed to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mit ſin, then to confeſſe their ſins to God, &amp; repent. As <hi>Nahaſh</hi> would haue had the right eyes of the people of <hi>Iabes Gilead</hi> to be put out,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 11.2.</note> &amp; to bring that ſhame vpon the <hi>Iſraelites:</hi> ſo that ſpirituall <hi>Nahaſh</hi> ſeeketh by his ſubtilty, to haue the right eie, wherby we are brought to the ſight &amp; know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of our ſins, to bee put out, and ſo to bring ſhame and confuſion vpon vs: like the Rauen, that firſt of all ſtriketh out the ſilly ſheepes eye, that he may not eſcape his tyranny: ſo Sathan would haue vs not to ſee the ſhame of our ſins: and when for want of ſhame we haue ſinned, he would haue vs aſhamed to confeſſe them, and repent.</p>
               <pb n="30" facs="tcp:8223:19" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>I read on a time, a pretty familiar hiſtory (a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greeable heereunto) of certaine religious and well diſpoſed perſons, confeſſing their ſinnes, to whom the Diuell approched; whom, when a godly and reuerend father eſpied, he asked him how he durſt, or to what end hee came ſo neere ſuch godly perſons at ſo good an exerciſe: who made this anſwere: I come (ſaid he) to reſtore that which long agone I haue taken from them. The godly man maruelling that the Diuell was become a reſtorer, (exceeding many Chriſtians that ſcarcely think on reſtitution) demanded of him what that was. Shame, ſaid he, which I took from the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miting of ſin, &amp; now I bring it to them againe, to keep them fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſing of their ſins. Thus we ſee that the Diuell would haue vs not to bee aſhamed to ſin, but aſhamed to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe our ſins &amp; repent: therfore whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we ſhould forſake our ſins, and follow Chriſt, if wee ſhall perceiue any vnwillingneſſe in vs to performe this duty, let vs know from whence it came: and ſo in deſpite of Sathan put off his viſard, and vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maske our ſelues, that wee may ſee theſe dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous <hi>caribdes,</hi> &amp; auoid them, and ſo follow <hi>Chriſt</hi> our precurſor, our grand-captaine &amp; protector.</p>
            </div>
            <div type="part">
               <head>The laſt part. <hi>As deere Children.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>CHildren in the Scripture are diuers wayes taken, beſides them that come of their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, bloud, and generation: and beſides them which are in the right deſcending line of the ſame linage or ſtocke.</p>
               <p>For ſometime ſubiects are called children:
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:8223:19" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>Dauid</hi> ſpake thus to <hi>Saul</hi> the King: <hi>My Father,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Sam. 24.12.</note> 
                  <hi>behold, behold, &amp;c.</hi> Thus <hi>Abimelech</hi> was called King and Father. Alſo theſe are called Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that ſucced others in title or right of inheri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance. Thus <hi>Ieconias,</hi> that neuer had childe, is ſayd to beget <hi>Salathiel,</hi> becauſe he was the next of <hi>Dauids</hi> ſtocke;<note place="margin">Ierem. 22.30.</note> who therefore ſucceded <hi>Ieco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias</hi> in the kingdome of <hi>Iudah.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They that are guided by the councell of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, are called children: ſo <hi>Ioſeph</hi> ſayd:<note place="margin">Gen. 45.8.</note> 
                  <hi>God hath made me a father to Pharaoh.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seruants ſometime are called children: The ſeruants of <hi>Naaman</hi> ſayd vnto him: <hi>Father,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Kings. 5.13.</note> 
                  <hi>if the Prophet had commanded thee a great thing, wouldſt not thou haue done it?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Yonger men and women are called children, in reſpect of their elders: <hi>Rebuke not an Elder,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Tim. 5.1.2.</note> 
                  <hi>but exhort him as a Father, the elder women as mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>They which are vnder the tuition or helpe of others, are called children: ſo <hi>Iob</hi> ſayd;<note place="margin">Iob. 29.16.</note> 
                  <hi>he was a father to the poore.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Scollers were called the ſonnes of the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets: <hi>Elizeus</hi> ſaid to <hi>Elias, My father, my father.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Kings. 2.12.</note>
               </p>
               <p>Hearers are called children in reſpect of their paſtors and teachers:<note place="margin">1. Kings 13.11.</note> 
                  <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith to the <hi>Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans; yee haue many teachers, but not many fathers.</hi> And to the <hi>Galat.</hi> he ſaith: <hi>My little children,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Gal. 4.19.</note> 
                  <hi>of whom I trauell in birth againe, vntil Chriſt be for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med in you.</hi> All true beleeuers are ſaid to be <hi>deere</hi> children in this Scripture, by the Apoſtles do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine, ſhewing his fatherly loue, and tender care ouer them that imitate Chriſt.<note place="margin">Rom. 9.8.</note> The true
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:8223:20"/> children of <hi>Abraham</hi> are they that imitate him in faith.</p>
               <p>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 21.28. Luke 15.11.</note>As in the parable of the Goſpell it is recor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, that a man had two ſonnes, the one perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming his fathers wil, the other neglecting it: the one frugall, the other prodigall. Likewiſe</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Abraham</hi> had two ſonnes, <hi>Iſmael</hi> and <hi>Iſaac,</hi> but <hi>Iſaac</hi> onely free-borne: ſo there are two ſorts of children; one, the children of God: the other, the children of the world.</p>
               <p>The children of God are they which are vnited to God by adoption, as Brothers and Siſters in Chriſt, by hearing of the word of God, &amp; kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping it. <hi>Theſe are my brethren</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>that heare the word, and keepe it.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The children of the world are they which fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion themſelues like vnto the world, ſetting &amp; ſetling their affections on worldly things: but the children of God are changed in their ſhape, by renewing of their minds, they are of another faſhion, they are of a new birth, of the ſpirituall kindred of Chriſt by regeneration. The childre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of God do follow Chriſt, the children of the world do follow it, and are led by it: but the chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of God are led by the ſpirit of God. The children of the world haue their whole truſt &amp; confidence in worldy things:<note place="margin">Rom. 8.14.</note> but the children of God are predeſtinated to bee his adopted children,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.5.</note> by faith in Chriſt. It is the greateſt pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ferment in this world, amongſt the children of the world, to be made the heire of a King, Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perour, or Prince, and to bee in great account with men in this world: but the children of God
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:8223:20"/> are of greater account with God and godly men, both in this world, and in the world to come.</p>
               <p>The children of Kings are attended by noble men, and great perſonages, and guarded with ſtrong men; yet all but men, whoſe breath is in their noſtrils, whoſe hands cannot accompliſh the deuiſes of their hearts: But the children of God are guided by God himſelfe, whoſe eye is alwayes ouer the righteous, they are guarded by Angels:<note place="margin">Pſalm. 34.15.</note> 
                  <hi>The Angels of God ſhall pitch their tents round about them that feare him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The children of the world doe take delight in ſuch pleaſures as the world doth affoord them; as carnall ſecurity, worldly proſperity, beaſtly ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſuality, couetouſneſſe, pride, luxury, idleneſſe, and ſuch like. But the pleaſures that God affoordeth his deere children, are ſuch as neither the world can giue them, nor take from them: As the loue of righteouſneſſe, delight in the law of God,<note place="margin">Pſalm. 1.2.</note> pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tience in affliction, loue of them that excell in vertue, and ſuch like.</p>
               <p>The riches of the children of the world, are gold, ſiluer, houſes, lands, lordſhips, rents, reuenues, and ſuch like: which theeues may ſteale, ruſt may fret, fire may conſume, water may drowne, plague may infect, time may weare out, and death may end. But the riches of Gods children are the word of God, firme faith, forgiueneſſe of ſins, freedome from hell, liberty with the Saints, the ſpirit of con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentation, peace of conſcience, continuall ioy in the holy Ghoſt; and a kingdome of glory in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, which no theefe can ſteale, no ruſt can cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rupt, no fire can conſume, no water can drowne,
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:8223:21" rendition="simple:additions"/> no plague can infect, no time can weare out, no death can end.</p>
               <p>The children of God are ſhrowded vnder the wings of his mercy; but the children of the world are ſubiect vnder the weapons of his iuſtice, and a fearefull thing it is to fall into the hands of God in ſuch a caſe. If the children, that were diſobedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ent to their parents in the time of the law, by the law were ſtoned to death for their diſobedience towards their earthly parents:<note place="margin">Deut. 21.21.</note> how much more are the wilfull and wicked children of the world in danger of the father of heauen, and God of heauen, and earth, for their diſloialty and diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience in forſaking God, and following the world? If the children of the righteous that of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend God haue not eſcaped Gods ſeuere puniſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, how ſhall the vngracious children of vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>godly parents abide it? If the ſonnes of <hi>Eli,</hi> and the ſonnes of <hi>Dauid</hi> were puniſhed by death, as the reward and wages of their ſinnes, without par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don or partiality; although <hi>Eli</hi> was the holy Prieſt of God, and <hi>Dauid</hi> the Princely Prophet of God: the one high in Gods fauour, the other as great in his loue. How then ſhal <gap reason="foreign">
                     <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                  </gap> the euill egge of a bad bird eſcape vncruſhed?<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> King. 2.23.24</note>
               </p>
               <p>If the children that mocked the prophet, were by Gods iudgement torne in peeces, and deuou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red of Beares: how ſhall theſe prophane ſcof<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fers, and deriders of the Goſpell, and profeſſors thereof eſcape Gods fearefull iudgements?</p>
               <p>God loueth thoſe children that imitate their parents good examples, and follow them as they follow Chriſt.</p>
               <pb n="35" facs="tcp:8223:21" rendition="simple:additions"/>
               <p>The Apoſtle in this our Text, maketh a diſtin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction betweene the children of God and the children of the world; terming the children of God, <hi>Deere Children.</hi> Deerely beloued, and deere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly are they purchaſed with the precious and priceleſſe bloud of his beſt loued Sonne Chriſt; whom as zealouſly they ought to follow for his grace,<note place="margin">2. Kings 2.</note> as <hi>Eliſha</hi> followed <hi>Elias</hi> for his mantle and ſpirit. If children follow their parents, and obey their precepts for an earthly and terreſtriall in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>heritance, ſhould we not much more obey our heauenly Father for an heauenly and coeleſtiall heritage, aſſured to his deere children, that fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low him, as he hath by his deerely beloued ſonne, in his ſacred word taught them.</p>
               <p>The manner how we ſhould follow him, is by the Apoſtle plainly expreſſed: to wit, <hi>As deere Children,</hi> according to Chriſts owne words; af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firming that whoſoeuer will enter into the king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome of heauen, muſt bee as a little Childe, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nocent, humble and meeke: Not clothed with couetouſneſſe, puffed with pride, nor with vo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>luptuouſneſſe: For to ſuch (ſaith Chriſt our pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſor) belongeth the Kingdome of heauen. Yong and vnacquainted with groſſe ſinnes are moſt fit to follow God in the prime-time of their yeares, in the maiden-head of their age, giuing him the firſt fruits of their loue.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Iohn</hi> the Apoſtle and Euangeliſt was knowne by the name of the Diſciple whom IESVS lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued. So was yong <hi>Samuel</hi> fauoured of God. So was <hi>Dauid,</hi> a man after Gods owne heart: for hee was a man that followed God from his youth.
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:8223:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> So was little <hi>Daniel,</hi> a great man with God: a lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle man amongſt men, but a great Prophet of God. This religious affection of vertuous youth Saint <hi>Paul</hi> learned of Chriſt, and taught it to his ſcholler <hi>Timothy,</hi> and other Churches which he had by the word planted. But if we ſeeke to vrge the youth of our time thereunto, they will thinke that wee come before our time; as though they might be licenced to run a wilfull and wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked courſe,<note place="margin">Math, 8, 29,</note> and will bee ready to tell vs (as the Diuell told Chriſt) that wee torment them be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their time. The Prodigall ſonne was the yonger.</p>
               <p>Chriſt our heauenly king is gone before vs, and hath opened the gate of heauen: otherwiſe there had beene no paſſage at all; yet he telleth vs, that the gate is ſtraight,<note place="margin">Math, 7, 14,</note> and there are few that enter in thereat: therefore we muſt ſtriue, ſtraine, and ſtoope, if we intend to enter in. Firſt, wee muſt ſtrippe our ſelues out of the old habite of ſinne: for if ſinne lye at the doore,<note place="margin">Gen. 4.7,</note> it will ſtop our paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſage, as it did <hi>Caines:</hi> whether it, theſe groſſe and grieuous ſinnes, or any other beloued ſin, which wee ſo tenderly harbour and foſter in our hearts, like a rocke, or an heape of ſand, will ſtoppe and damme vp the gate. Therefore we muſt, like little children, creep low, and humble our ſelues: for if wee put on the true habit of humility and meeke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, Sathan cannot hinder vs. As the Serpents will not come into the vineyard when vines bring forth their bloſſomes, no more will the old Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent, and author of pride come neere vs, if we, like fruitfull branches, bud the bloſſomes of humility.
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:8223:22" rendition="simple:additions"/> The want of this vertue caſt <hi>Nebuchadnezar</hi> out of his earthly Kingdome, and we muſt haue it or elſe we ſhall not enter into the heauenly Kingdome. The Phariſee ſwelled in his owne proud conceit, and therefore hee was too bigge to enter in, but the poore Publican ſtooped and went in, little <hi>Zacheus</hi> was a great rich man, but he diminiſh'd himſelfe by reſtitution &amp; giuing to the poore, he deſcended from the lofty branches to the roote of humility, and ſo entred in. This gate (it ſhould ſeeme) was made for none to enter, but for theſe that are as children.<note place="margin">Math. 18.3.</note> 
                  <hi>Verily I ſay vnto you</hi> (ſaith Chriſt) <hi>except yee become as little children, yee can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not enter into the kingdome of God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>How acceptable is the morning ſacrifice of our tender age vnto God, no ſacrifice of beaſts was more welcome to God then yong kids or lambs, none of birds more acceptable then yong pige<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons or Turtle doues: Manna was to be gathered in the morning before the Sun aroſe.</p>
               <p>If we follow God as deere children, God will take vs for his children, and this is no ſmall ſigne of Gods mercy, ſo much to fauour, and ſo high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly to grace vs with the title of his children, that wee may call him father: Well, and worthily may he be called a father, for he is <hi>omnium Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor fidelium<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> Pater,</hi> the Creator of all men and Father of the faithfull, and therefore it is written, <hi>Is not hee thy Father that hath bought thee, and that made thee, and proportioned thee?</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 32.6.</note> Yea without doubt, God is our Father, if we will obey him, an euerliuing and an euerlaſting Father, as it is alſo written: <hi>Doubtleſſe, thou art our Father,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eſay 63.16.</note> 
                  <hi>though</hi> A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>braham
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:8223:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> 
                  <hi>be ignorant of vs, and</hi> Iſrael <hi>know vs not, yet thou ô Lord art our Father and our Redeemer, thy name is for euer.</hi> If he be our Father, and our Lord, we ſhould honour and feare him.<note place="margin">Mallac. 1.6.</note> 
                  <hi>A ſonne hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth his father, and a ſeruant his maiſter, If then I bee a Father where is my honour? If I bee a Maiſter where is my feare, ſaith the Lord of Hoſts? If therefore ye call him Father,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1. Pet. 1.17.</note> 
                  <hi>which without reſpect of perſons iudgeth according to euery mans worke, paſſe the time of your dwelling here in feare,</hi> ſaith the Apoſtle.</p>
               <p>In all our miſeries and feare we are imboldened by the Spirit of Chriſt to call God our Father, as we may reade:<note place="margin">Gal. 4.6.</note> 
                  <hi>Becauſe yee are ſonnes, God hath ſent the Spirit of his Sonne into your hearts, which cryeth Abba Father.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Math. 23.9.</note> Wherefore Chriſt commandeth vs to call no man father on earth, (that is, in faith and religion) a reaſon he giueth, ſaying: <hi>There is but one your Father which is in heauen,</hi> he is a father that made both body and ſoule, and is ready to ſaue both, when earthly parents forſake vs, he will take vs; when they leaue vs, he will receiue vs; when they will not, and cannot help vs, he can and will help vs; when they dye, hee liueth, for hee is an euerlaſting and an euerliuing Father: firſt and laſt, the beginning and the end, a beginning, without beginning, and an end without end.</p>
               <p>Many children bragge and boaſt of their pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents gentry, and they accompt it a great honour to be called the ſonne of a King, as <hi>Dauid</hi> ſaid, when hee ſhould marry <hi>Sauls</hi> daughter, <hi>Doe you thinke it a ſmall thing to be a Kings ſonne?</hi> Should the children of God thinke it a ſmall thing to be
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:8223:23" rendition="simple:additions"/> the ſonnes and daughters of the King of Kings, and Lord of all Lords, King of heauen and earth?</p>
               <p>He is worthily called a Father, for he is.</p>
               <list>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pater ſanctitatis.</hi> The Father of ſanctity.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pater poteſtatis.</hi> The Father of power.</item>
                  <item>
                     <hi>Pater pietatis.</hi> The Father of piety.</item>
               </list>
               <p>The Father of ſanctity and holyneſſe, and therefore Chriſt ſaith;<note place="margin">Iohn 17.17.</note> 
                  <hi>Father ſanctifie them in the truth.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The father of power, becauſe hee can doe all things, therefore he that knew beſt, ſaid;<note place="margin">Mark. 14.36.</note> 
                  <hi>All things are poſsible to thee.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The Father of piety and mercy, and therefore the Apoſtle calleth him, <hi>The Father of mercy,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2. Cor. 1.3.</note> 
                  <hi>and God of conſolation.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seeing he is the Father of mercy we ought to pray to him with deuotion, For Chriſt ſaith, <hi>Whatſoeuer yee ſhall aske the Father in my name,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iohn 16.23.</note> 
                  <hi>he will giue it you.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seeing he is the Father of power we ought to honour him, with humble obedience: therefore the Holy-Ghoſt by the Prophet <hi>Malachy</hi> ſaith:<note place="margin">Mallac. 1.6.</note> 
                  <hi>The Sonne honoureth the Father, &amp;c.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Seeing he is the Father of mercy, we ought to follow and imitate him in mercy; as Chriſt com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mandeth vs, ſaying:<note place="margin">Luk. 6.36.</note> 
                  <hi>Bee yee mercifull as your Father is mercifull.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>And ſeeing he is the Father of power, of holy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe and mercy, of him as dutifull children, wee ſhould (bowing the knees of hearts) ſeeke a bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nng: <hi>Iſaac</hi> his ſonne ſaid to his father, <hi>Haſt thou
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:8223:24"/> but one bleſsing:</hi> But the God of <hi>Abraham, Iſaac,</hi> and <hi>Iacob</hi> hath a bleſſing for euery faithfull child of his, yea a triple benediction: <hi>Benedictio preueni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ens, benedictio adiuuans, &amp; benedictio conſummans,</hi> His bleſſing preuenting, his bleſſing aſſiſting, and his bleſſing conſummating or finiſhing: The firſt of his mercy, the ſecond of his grace, the third of his glory; The firſt of our conuerſion, the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond of our conuerſation, the third of our glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rification.</p>
               <p>The firſt Benediction: <hi>Bleſſed is he to whom the Lord imputeth no ſinne: Bleſſed is he whoſe ſinnes are remitted.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The ſecond: <hi>Bleſſed is the man that feareth the Lord and walkes in his waies.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>The third and laſt benediction: <hi>Come yee bleſſed children of my Father, receiue the kingdome pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for you from the beginning of the world.</hi>
               </p>
               <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
               <pb facs="tcp:8223:24" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
